Guide to the Richard Lawrence Day Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Richard Lawrence Day papers
1941-2005
1978-1989
MS 1822
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
The papers consist of articles, correspondence, photographs, publications, and other research materials documenting Dr. Day's studies of the Heimlich maneuver and the ensuing reactions of the medical profession and general public. The papers also contain brief biographical information and a few materials related to other research topics such as oxygen-induced vasoconstriction.
Day, Richard Lawrence, 1905-1989
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sarah D. Perreten, 2003; Dr. Arthur Dubois, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Lawrence Day was born in New York, New York, on March 28, 1905. He attended Harvard University, where he received a B.S. degree in 1927 and an M.D. degree in 1931. From 1933 to 1953, Day was associate professor at the College of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University. Day then served as professor and chairman of the department of pediatrics at the Downstate Medical Center, Brooklyn (1953-1960) and at the University of Pittsburgh (1960-1965). From 1965 to 1968, Day was national medical director of Planned Parenthood. Day then taught at Mount Sinai School of Medicine from 1968 until his retirement in 1971. During the 1980s, Day studied the effects of the Heimlich maneuver to treat choking. After demonstrating the superiority of this technique to back blows, Day successfully petitioned the American Red Cross and American Heart Association to change their recommendations. Day also researched topics in neonatology and is noted for his study of body temperature control in premature babies and jaundice in newborns. Day died on June 15, 1989.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of articles, correspondence, photographs, publications, and other research materials documenting Dr. Day's studies of the Heimlich maneuver and the ensuing reactions of the medical profession and general public. The papers also contain brief biographical information and a few materials related to other research topics such as oxygen-induced vasoconstriction.
Asphyxia; First aid in illness and injury; Heimlich maneuver; Day, Richard Lawrence, 1905-1989; Heimlich, Henry J., 1920-2016
- Inventory, 1941-2003
  Scope and Contents
  The Richard Lawrence Day papers are arranged under three headings: Biographical information, Heimlich maneuver, and Other research. The majority of the collection documents Day's study of the Heimlich maneuver in the 1980s, though there are also a few materials related to Day's overall career and other research interests.
  Biographical information includes career sketches and a retrospective account of Day's involvement in choking research, written by his close colleague, Dr. Arthur B. Dubois.
  Heimlich maneuver consists of a variety of records related to Day's research of the Heimlich maneuver including: correspondence with the American Red Cross, William H. Montgomery (chairman, American Heart Association), Henry J. Heimlich and others; Day's studies of choking in infants; medical and general reactions to the Heimlich maneuver; criticism of the Heimlich maneuver by Drs. Joseph S. Redding and Peter Safar; and general research materials. The heading also includes several of Day's writings, including the article, "Choking: The Heimlich abdominal thrust vs. back blows: An approach to measurement of inertial and aerodynamic forces" (1982), two speeches, and letters to the editor reacting to criticism.
  Other research contains scattered reprints of Day's earlier publications and some research materials related to studies on topics such as oxygen-induced vasoconstriction.
  - Biographical information, 1979-1989, 2003, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Heimlich maneuver
    - General correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Red Cross, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Heimlich, Henry J. [includes writings], 1975-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Injury to infants, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Montgomery, William H., 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Post-mortem examination of infants, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Press, 1974-1985, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Redding, Joseph S. [criticism of Heimlich maneuver], 1979-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Research materials, 1976-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 10 - 12)
    - Safar, Peter [criticism of Heimlich maneuver], 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Writings
      - American Heart Association speech, 1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - "Choking: The Heimlich abdominal thrust vs. back blows: An approach to measurement of inertial and aerodynamic forces" [article; includes photographs], 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Howland Award speech, 1973-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Letters to the editor, 1982-1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Other research, 1941-1954, 1975, 1984-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)